{"tossups": [{"question": "Jess Gorkin of<em> Parade</em> Magazine proposed a system that was implemented after this event. It ended with a secret agreement to remove Jupiter installations in Turkey, which convinced Nikita Khrushchev to dismantle his own weapon systems. The Washington-to-Moscow hotline was created after, for the point, what thirteen-day crisis in which the U.S. blockaded an island nation over the placement of nuclear weapons?", "answer": "<b> Cuban missile</b> crisis (accept equivalent descriptions)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The Koori and Noongar are two subgroups of these people. A false legend claims that, until a 1967 constitutional referendum, these people were legally classified as \u201cfauna;\u201d that referendum did stop the exclusion of these people from their country\u2019s census. In 2008, Kevin Rudd apologized for the \u201cStolen Generations,\u201d in which children of these people were taken by the state. Over 100,000 of these people currently live in New South Wales. For the point, give this term for people indigenous to Australia before British colonization.", "answer": "<b> Aborigines</b> (or<b> Aboriginal</b> Australians; accept<b> indigenous Australian</b>s before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this German mathematician, the namesake of the normal distribution in statistics and two of Maxwell\u2019s four equations.", "answer": "Carl Frederic<b> Gauss</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {}, {"question": "To impress Diane Nguyen [win], part of this structure is stolen by a drunken Bojack Horseman. In 2004\u2019s<em> The Day After Tomorrow</em>, a tornado destroys it; so does the original<em> Sharknado</em>, as it scales Mount Lee. It originally referenced a housing development in the nearby hills and included the word \u201cLAND\u201d. For the point, name this 45-foot-tall sign, a cultural landmark overlooking, and advertising the name of, the film district of Los Angeles.", "answer": "the<b> Hollywood</b>(land) Sign (accept<b> Hollywoo</b> Sign)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Piedmontese forces crushed the Chevalier de Belle Isle at the Battle of Assietta during this conflict, which saw the British beaten at Fontenoy by Maurice de Saxe. The Battle of Dettingen, fought in this war, was the last time a British monarch led troops into battle, and Louisbourg was captured during this war\u2019s American phase, King George\u2019s War. The War of Jenkin\u2019s Ear was a subsidiary of this war, which was sparked by Frederick the Great\u2019s invasion of Silesia. For the point, name this war, caused by resistance to the Pragmatic Sanction and the inheritance of Empress Maria Theresa.", "answer": "War of the<b> Austrian Succession</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In this year, a December 12th \u201csafe harbor\u201d deadline caused the Supreme Court to deliver a ruling one day after hearing oral arguments. In this year\u2019s election, the runner-up candidate requested that four counties, including Broward, recount ballots amidst technical problems caused by \u201changing chads.\u201d Ralph Nader\u2019s Green Party candidacy in this year may have contributed to a narrow Democratic loss in Florida. For the point, name this presidential election, essentially decided by the Supreme Court\u2019s decision in<em> Bush</em> <em>v. Gore</em>.", "answer": "Election of<b> 2000</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This composer of incidental music for<em> Sigurd Jorsalfar</em> wrote a suite for string orchestra \u201cin olden style\u201d to celebrate Ludwig Holberg. His incidental music for another play includes a section in which a B minor theme increases in speed and volume as the title character is chased by trolls and goblins. For the point, \u201cMorning Mood\u201d and \u201cIn The Hall of the Mountain King\u201d are from what Norwegian composer\u2019s <em>Peer Gynt Suite</em>?", "answer": "Edvard Hagerup<b> Grieg</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Actor Joseph Estrada stole $80 million as this country\u2019s president but was pardoned by his successor, Gloria Arroyo. Corazon Aquino rose to lead this country via the People Power Revolution, ending a kleptocracy in which this nation\u2019s First Lady amassed a large collection of shoes. Imelda and Ferdinand Marcos once ruled, for the point, what Asian island country where the President resides in Malaca\u02dcnan Palace in Manila?", "answer": "Republic of the<b> Philippines</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This President sent John Coffey and John Eaton to negotiate the Treaty of Dancing Rabbit Creek. This man fired Robert Randolph for embezzling from the Navy, and Richard Lawrence made this man the first U.S. President to be the subject of an attempted assassination. He appointed Roger Taney to the Supreme Court and fought with Nicholas Biddle over the Second Bank of the United States. The Indian Removal Act was passed by, for the point, what seventh U.S. President?", "answer": "Andrew<b> Jackson</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One of these documents with \u201ceight legs\u201d was part of the civil service exam in the Ming dynasty. One work in this form describes the arithmetic and geometric growth rates of food production and population, respectively, and was written by Robert Malthus. This literary genre includes two,<em> on Criticism</em> and <em>on Man</em>, by Alexander Pope, and one<em> Concerning Human Understanding</em> by John Locke. Michel de Montaigne [mon-TAYN] invented, for the point, what type of argumentative, scholarly writing often performed by students applying to colleges?", "answer": "<b> essay</b> (accept any additional information)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "In November 2015, bomb threats grounded two Air France flights leaving this city\u2019s airport, where a TSA officer was shot in 2013. In 2015, a threat that 33 \u201ccomrades\u201d had planted bombs and timed nerve gas agents claimed to target every school in this city\u2019s Unified District, causing the school board and Mayor Eric Garcetti to close over 1,000 schools. For the point, name this California city where the Millennium Plot, an attack on LAX Airport, was foiled in 2000.", "answer": "<b> Los Angeles</b> (or<b> L.A.</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "One man replaced Ann Richards in this position after rumors that Richards\u2019 staff was \u201cdominated by lesbians\u201d were spread by a campaign run by Karl Rove. During a Presidential debate, another former holder of this position couldn\u2019t remember a third Cabinet department he would cut. Greg Abbott currently serves in, for the point, what post formerly held by George W. Bush and Rick Perry, the leader of the largest continental U.S. state?", "answer": "<b> Governor of Texas</b> (prompt on partial answer)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Cellist Vedran Smailovi\u00b4c was known for performing in ruined buildings during one siege of this city. Artillery blast marks filled with red resin, known as the \u201croses\u201d of this city, were caused during a siege that was lifted by the Dayton Accords. Another event in this city prompted the July Crisis, and was orchestrated by Danilo Ilic [ill-itch]. That event saw the death of Sophie of Hohenberg and the arrest of Black Hand member Gavrilo Princip. Archduke Franz Ferdinand was assassinated in, for the point, what city, the capital of Bosnia?", "answer": "<b> Sarajevo</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Genghis Khan refused to adopt this religion\u2019s dietary customs after encountering it at Bukhara. The Hui and Uyghur [wee-gur] peoples are Chinese minorities who practice this religion. Article 160 defines Malay people as following this religion. This religion\u2019s Qiblah was changed in its \u201cCow\u201d sura to no longer point to Jerusalem, and quotations from this religion\u2019s prophet are collected in hadiths. Shia and Sunni branches make up, for the point, what religion, whose holy book is the Quran?", "answer": "<b> Islam</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This country disappointed the June Democracy Movement by postponing democratic reform until after it hosted the 1988 Summer Olympics. One president of this country was convicted due to his role in the Gwangju Massacre. This country has been referred to as the \u201cMiracle on the Han River\u201d due to its economic boom in the 20th century. For the point, name this country which will host the 2018 Winter Olympics in Pyeongchang on an East Asian peninsula.", "answer": "<b> South Korea</b> (or<b> Republic of Korea</b> or<b> ROK</b>; prompt on Korea; do not accept North Korea or the Democratic People\u2019s Republic of Korea)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This event was instigated by a declaration at the Old South Meeting House that \u201cthis meeting can do nothing more to save the country!\u201d The<em> Beaver</em>,<em> Eleanor</em>, and<em> Dartmouth</em> were raided during this event, which took place at Griffin\u2019s Wharf. The Intolerable Acts were passed in response to, for the point, what 1773 incident in which members of the Sons of Liberty, dressed as Mohawk Indians, dumped crates into Boston Harbor?", "answer": "<b> Boston Tea Party</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Michael Jones suggested founding a Welsh colony in this country\u2019s Chubut Province. The Tehuelche [te-whel-chay] people, who were nicknamed for their large leather shoes, are indigenous to this country\u2019s share of Patagonia. The tallest mountain in the Western Hemisphere, Aconcagua, is located in this nation\u2019s portion of the Andes. Tierra del Fuego at the tip of South America is owned by, for the point, what country with capital Buenos Aires?", "answer": "<b> Argentina</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "During this event, its subject remembered that he owed Asclepius a rooster and asked Crito to pay the debt. This event, which was depicted at the end of the<em> Phaedo</em>, was required after its subject was found guilty of corrupting the youth of Athens and forced to consume hemlock. For the point, name this event in which the teacher of Plato committed court-ordered suicide.", "answer": "the<b> death</b> of<b> Socrates</b> (prompt on Phaedo before mentioned; accept descriptive equivalents)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "Colonel John By built one of these in Upper Canada, near modern Ottawa, to help evade American attacks. Another of these was built over the Niagara Escarpment and was known as DeWitt Clinton\u2019s \u201cbig ditch.\u201d Gamal Abdel Nasser nationalized one of these, which was built without locks, in Egypt, leading to a 1956 crisis. For the point, name these man-made waterways, including the Rideau, Erie, and Suez.", "answer": "<b> canal</b>s (accept Rideau Canal, Erie Canal, or Suez Canal)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "One athlete from this country had her silver medal from the 2012 Olympic 800-meter event disputed because of concerns over her true gender. Another athlete from this home of Caster Semenya was found guilty of culpable homicide in 2014, then of murder in 2015, for the death of his girlfriend, Reeva Steenkamp. For the point, name this African country represented by a man who wore Flex-Foot Cheetah racing blades, Oscar Pistorius, who was imprisoned in Pretoria.", "answer": "Republic of<b> South Africa</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A Jean-Antoine Houdon sculpture of this man in his military uniform stands in the rotunda of the Virginia State Capitol Building. Constantino Brumidi created an<em> Apotheosis</em> of this man, who was the subject of Gilbert Stuart\u2019s<em> Lansdowne Portrait</em>. Grand Wood\u2019s painting<em> Parson Weems\u2019 Fable</em> shows this figure as a child, after he cut down a cherry tree. For the point, name this man, who Emanuel Leutze [LOYT-zuh] painted<em> Crossing the Delaware</em>.", "answer": "George<b> Washington</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The Act establishing this organization names maximum employment, price stability, and long-term interest rate stability as its three goals. This organization uses monetary policy to meet those goals, as in December 2015 when its Board of Governors announced a quarter-point increase in the federal funds rate. Alan Greenspan and Ben Bernanke once led, for the point, what central banking system of the United States, now chaired by Janet Yellen?", "answer": "<b> Federal Reserve</b> System (prompt on the Fed)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {}, {"question": "Prior to the Final Solution, this location was proposed by Franz Rademacher as a destination for European Jews. In this present-day nation, Ranavalona III was the last monarch of the Merina Kingdom; that kingdom was replaced by French colonial rule in 1897 and by the Malagasy Republic in 1958. Antananarivo is the capital of, for the point, what large island country off the southwest coast of Africa?", "answer": "Republic of<b> Madagascar</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}